Guide to the Robert W. Straub Oral History Project 2003-2007
Western Oregon University Archives
Robert W. Straub Oral History Project
2003-2007
MSS 23
Western Oregon University Archives 345 N. Monmouth Ave. http://www.wou.edu/provost/library/archives/ Monmouth, OR, 97361 503-838-8893 libarchives@wou.edu
5.0 linear feet 127 Hi8, Digital8, and MiniDV tapes, 1 audiocassette tape, 148 DVDs, 5 VHS tapes, and 1 box of textual materials
The Robert W. Straub Oral History Project, commissioned by the Robert W. Straub Archives Advisory Board and conducted by oral historian Michael O'Rourke, documents the life and legacy of former Oregon governor Bob Straub through the testimony of family, friends, and colleagues. Interview subjects include Straub's wife Pat and several of their children, as well as former Oregon governors Barbara Roberts, Neil Goldschmidt, and Victor Atiyeh. The collection includes video recordings of interviews, transcriptions, and research materials.
The collection is open to the public. Patrons may view DVD access copies where they exist; please check with the archives regarding access conditions for audiovisual materials not on DVD.
The project was commissioned by the Robert W. Straub Archives Advisory Board. Interview tapes were transferred to the Archives after the project's completion, and photocopies of Michael O’Rourke’s interview research materials were made for the Archives in 2012. DVD access copies of most tapes were created from 2006-2007. Transcripts for two tapes of Janet McLennan’s interview and excerpts from an interview of Ken Johnson and Janet McLennan were created by Western Oregon University Archives student employee Libby Salisbury.
This oral history collection complements the Robert W. Straub Collection, also held at Western Oregon University. The Straub collection includes an oral history conducted with Straub by the Oregon Historical Society, and also includes the papers of Straub's wife, Pat. Straub's official gubernatorial papers, as well as official records from his service as State Treasurer, are held at the Oregon State Archives.
Also at the WOU Archives are the papers of one of the interviewees, Janet McLennan.
The personal papers of interviewee Victor Atiyeh are held at Pacific University, while his official gubernatorial papers are held at the Oregon State Archives.
The papers of interviewee Barbara Roberts are held at Portland State University, while her official gubernatorial papers are held at the Oregon State Archives.
The records of interviewee Neil Goldchmidt's gubernatorial administration are held at the Oregon State Archives.
A collection of interviewee Floyd McKay's broadcasts from his time as a newscaster are held by the Oregon Historical Society.
The papers of interviewee Monroe Sweetland are held by the Oregon Historical Society.
The project contains interviews with 32 subjects, primarily friends and family of Robert Straub. These oral history interviews capture memories of Straub's personality, family life, leadership, and politics. The collection consists of video recordings, edited excerpts, research materials, transcriptions, correspondence, and inventories. Original video recordings are found on Hi8 tapes, Digital8 tapes, and MiniDV videocassettes. DVD access copies have been created for most materials. Particularly extensive interviews were conducted with Barbara Roberts, Pat Straub, Len Bergstein, Ken Johnson, and Janet McLennan.
Biographical/Historical note
Sponsored by Western Oregon University and administrated by the Robert W. Straub Archives Advisory Board, led by former Governor Victor Atiyeh, the Robert W. Straub Oral History Project’s goal was to create a research resource regarding Oregon's political, economic, and social history to complement the Robert W. Straub Collection. Friends, family, and colleagues of Straub were interviewed regarding their backgrounds, their relationship with Straub, and their recollections of him, both as a politician and as a person.
Interviews were videotaped and conducted by oral historian Michael O'Rourke, usually in the interview subject's home. Ellen Beckett was contracted by the Straub Oral History Project to create a transcript of Neil Goldschmidt's interview. Some later work on the project was done by Keni Sturgeon, who served as project coordinator. Funding was provided by private donations; a lack of funding prevented the project from fulfilling its original goal of 100 interviews. These recordings were utilized by Charles (Chuck) Johnson in writing his biography of Straub, Standing at the Water's Edge.
For brief biographical information about individual interviewees, please see their entries in the Interviews series.
The project documentation has been divided into two series:
Series I. Research materials Series II. Interviews
Series I contains O'Rourke's research materials in preparation for his interviews, arranged primarily by interview subject.
Series II contains oral histories and transcripts. Interviews have been arranged alphabetically by interview subject, with interview tapes for each subject arranged chronologically. The final subseries contains excerpts of interviews, edited by oral historian Michael O'Rourke for presentation to the Straub Archives Advisory Board or for other promotional purposes. These have been arranged chronologically.
Items are physically arranged by format:
Box 1: Textual materials
Box 2: Audiocassette, Hi8 tapes, and Digital8 tapes
Box 3: MiniDV tapes for interviews A-S
Box 4: MiniDV tapes for interviews T-W, as well as for an excerpt; VHS tapes; DVDs; CD
Box 5: Barbara Roberts interview DVDs, 10/22/2004-6/13/2005
Box 6: Barbara Roberts interview DVDs, 6/21/2005-3/31/2006
Straub, Robert W.
Robert W. Straub Oral History Project--Interviews; Lane County (Or.). Board of Commissioners; Oregon Investment Council; Oregon. Governor (1975-1979: Straub); Oregon. Legislative Assembly; Oregon. Treasurer's Office
Straub family
Oregon; Pacific Coast (Or.); Portland; Salem; Salem (Or.)
Elections; Finance; Investments; Mentally ill--Care--Oregon; Oregon--Politics and government--1951-; Political activities and groups
Environmental Activism; Mental Health; Political Campaigns
Anderson, Clayton; Atiyeh, Victor; Bentley, Sara; Bergstein, Len, (Leonard); Brickeen, Bob, (Robert); Brooks, Dean; Carson, Wally, (Wallace); George, Jim, (James); Goldschmidt, Neil E., 1940-; Hanneman, Barbara; Holman, Ralph; Johnson, Ken, (Kenneth Everett), 1928-2011; Kramer, Bud; Linde, Hans; Linde, Helen; McCall, Audrey; McKay, Floyd J.; McLennan, Janet; Meier, Roger; Miller, Fred; O'Rourke, Michael; Redden, Jim; Rippey, Jim; Roberts, Barbara, 1936-; Russell, Jean; Shepherd, Ruth; Straub, Jeff; Straub, Mike, (Michael); Straub, Pat, (Lana Laine Patricia); Sweetland, Monroe; Thomas, Patty, (Patricia Straub); Thomas, Peggy, (Margaret Straub); Wyss, Loren
Moving images; Oral histories
- Research Materials
  Except for the Administrative file, all materials in the Research Materials series were photocopied by the University Archivist from oral historian Michael O'Rourke's personal research files. A file listing in the Administrative file details the original folder labeling; in processing, combined files have been separated by individual, naming has been normalized, and the files have been alphabetized.
  Though the exact content of O'Rourke's files on each interviewee vary, most include some biographical materials and notes or an outline about possible interview questions; some also include pre-interview correspondence from O'Rourke to the interviewee letting him or her know some topics that will be discussed. Interview files are not present for Clayton Anderson, Audrey McCall, Fred Miller, Jim Redden, Barbara Roberts, Jean Russell, or Ruth Shepherd.
  - Administrative materials, 2005-2007, undated
    List of folder titles from O'Rourke's original research file names; interview list with notes; list of tapes transferred to the project manager; tape inventories; note from Michael O'Rourke to Mike Straub regarding an excerpt prepared for a board meeting
  - Straub Filing, miscellaneous, 2003-2007
    Includes project members' contact information, O'Rourke's email correspondence with Western Oregon University Professor Gary Jensen, minutes for a Straub Archives Advisory Board meeting, and photocopied research articles.
  - Straub Release Forms, 2003-2007
    Blank release form, checklist for releases, and an explanation of the release agreement for interviewees. This file does not contain any completed release forms.
  - Atiyeh, Victor, 2004
  - Bentley, Sara, 2005
  - Bergstein, Len, 2005-2006
  - Brickeen, Bob, 2005
  - Brooks, Dean, 2005
  - Carson, Wally, 2005
  - George, Jim, 2003-2004
  - Goldschmidt, Neil, 2005
  - Hanneman, Barbara, 2003-2004
  - Holman, Ralph, 2004
  - Johnson, Ken, 2003-2004
  - Kramer, Bud, 2005
  - Linde, Hans, 2004
  - McKay, Floyd, 2003-2004
  - McLennan, Janet, 2003-2004
  - Meier, Roger, 2003-2004
  - Rippey, Jim, 2006
  - Straub, Jeff, 2005
  - Straub, Mike, 2005
  - Straub, Pat, 2003
  - Thomas, Patty Straub, 2005
  - Thomas, Peggy Straub, 2005
  - Sweetland, Monroe, 2004
  - Wyss, Loren, 2005
- Interviews
  - Anderson, Clayton, 2005
    Clayton Anderson, a personal friend of Straub's, served as director of the Willamalane Parks and Recreation District in Springfield, Oregon, worked for the Oregon State Highway Commission dealing with outdoor recreation issues, and briefly headed Washington's state park system.
    - 9/16/2005
      Formats: 2 MiniDV tapes, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:29, 12:40
  - Atiyeh, Victor, 2004
    Victor Atiyeh served as Oregon's 32nd governor from 1979-1987. He ran against Straub as the Republican nominee for governor in 1974 and 1978, defeating Straub in the latter election. Prior to serving as governor, Atiyeh was president of the family rug business, Atiyeh Bros., Inc., and served in the Oregon legislature as a State Senator.
    - 9/22/2004
      Formats: 1 Hi8 tape, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:45
      The interview focuses on Straub's political career, particularly Atiyeh's assessment of Straub's service as State Treasurer and discussion of the 1974 gubernatorial campaign, the first in which Atiyeh and Straub competed against each other.
    - 10/22/2004
      Formats: 2 Hi8 tapes, 3 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:13 and 12:03
      The interview focuses on Straub's political career, particularly Atiyeh's assessment of Straub's service as Governor and discussion of the 1978 gubernatorial campaign, the last in which Atiyeh and Straub competed against each other.
  - Bentley, Sara, 2005
    Sara Bentley served as publisher of the Salem Statesman Journal from 1988-2001. She and Straub worked together on affordable housing issues, and Bentley served on the board of the Oregon Housing Council, which Straub chaired.
    - 2/9/2005
      Length: 1:02:28, 35:30
  - Bergstein, Len, 2005
    Leonard J. (Len) Bergstein, a political consultant and lobbyist, served as Straub's campaign manager in 1978, and served on Straub's gubernatorial staff as an administrative assistant, where he was involved in duties like screening political appointments and working as a legislative aide. Bergstein founded Northwest Strategies, Inc., a consulting firm, worked as a political analyst for KGW-TV, and served as an administrative assistant to Portland Mayor Neil Goldschmidt.
    - 2/25/2005
      Length: 1:02:27, 26:25
    - 3/25/2005
      Formats: 1 MiniDV tape, 1 DVD access copy
      Length: 1:13:00
    - 4/25/2005, 4/29/2005
      Length: 40:08
    - 6/29/2005
      Length: 48:34
      Bergstein discusses transportation issues such as the Mt Hood Freeway and Glen Jackson's interactions with Straub, among other topics.
    - 5/31/2006
      Formats: 2 MiniDV tapes, 1 DVD access copy
      Length: 1:02:16, 15:58
      Topics discussed include Straub's 1978 gubernatorial campaign.
    - 6/13/2006
      Length: 1:02:33, 1:02:20
  - Brickeen, Bob, 2005
    Robert (Bob) Brickeen, a State Police Captain, served as Straub's driver and handled Straub's personal security while he was governor. Prior to that, Brickeen was also the driver for Gov. Tom McCall.
    - 2/12/2005
      Length: 1:02:30, 32:00
      Brickeen discusses his experiences driving for Straub and for Gov. McCall, as well as his general experience with the Oregon State Police and his personal background.
  - Brooks, Dean, 2005
    Dr. Dean Brooks, a friend of Straub's, served as superintendant of the Oregon State Hospital for 27 years, during which time he also played the role of Dr. Spivey in the film One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest.
    - 2/11/2005
      Formats: 2 MiniDV tapes, 6 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:26, 1:02:00
      Brooks discusses his friendship with Straub, his service at the Oregon State Mental Hospital, his personal background, and his interactions with other Oregon politicians.
  - Carson, Wally, 2005
    Wallace P. (Wally) Carson, Jr., served in the Oregon state senate and then as a judge, beginning as a Marion County Circuit Court judge and moving up to the Oregon Supreme Court, where he became Oregon's longest-serving Chief Justice.
    - 2/28/2005
      Length: 1:02:28, 33:20
  - George, Jim, 2003-2004
    James (Jim) George was an investment manager for the Oregon State Treasurer's office for 25 years, including during Straub's administration, and was a personal friend of Straub's. He later served as investment manager for the Oregon Investment Council.
    - 11/24/2003
      Formats: 2 Digital8 tapes, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 59:52, 50:17
    - 2/10/2004
      Length: 1:01:49, 33:00
  - Goldschmidt, Neil, 2005
    Neil Goldschmidt served as Oregon's 33rd governor, from 1987-1991. Prior to that he served as mayor of Portland and as U.S. Secretary of Transportation. Goldschmidt first met the Straubs when he worked as an intern on Straub's 1964 campaign for treasurer; he became a close family friend, and lived with the family for a summer.
    - 6/23/2005
      Formats: 3 MiniDV tapes, 6 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:33, 57:50, 10:30
      Transcript: Printed copy, Word document file on CD
      The interview, conducted in Goldschmidt's Dundee, Oregon home, included discussion of Goldschmidt's background, Straub's campaigns, the Nestucca Spit highway issue, partisan politics, and Straub's Alzheimer's Disease.
  - Hanneman, Barbara, 2003-2004
    Barbara Hanneman served as Straub's personal secretary while he was treasurer and governor; prior to that she served on Gov. Robert Holmes' secretarial staff, and she later served as executive assistant to Senate President Ed Fadeley. She and her husband Gene remained close friends with the Straub family after Straub left office.
    - 10/8/2003
      Formats: 2 Digital8 tapes, 1 DVD access copy
      Length: 1:01:48, 49:00
    - 4/14/2004
      Formats: 2 Hi8 tapes, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:47, 45:20
  - Holman, Ralph, 2004
    Ralph M. Holman, an attorney and judge, served as an Oregon Supreme Court Associate Justice from 1965-1980.
    - 10/20/2004
      Length: 1:00:59, 44:07
    - 11/4/2004
      Length: 1:02:30, 1:02:23, 49:19
  - Johnson, Ken, 2003-2004
    Kenneth (Ken) Johnson served as Deputy State Treasurer under Straub, and as administrative aide for economics and as deputy director of the executive department in Straub's gubernatorial administration. He served as aide and advisor to several other Oregon governors as well--Bob Holmes, Tom McCall, and Neil Goldschmidt--and served as press editor of Salem's Capitol Press. His son Charles (Chuck) went on to write a biography of Straub.
    - 7/28/2003
      Length: 1:01:12, 33:00
    - 10/28/2003
      Formats: 2 Digital8 tapes, 4 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:46, 1:01:48
    - 2/3/2004
      Formats: 3 Digital8 tapes, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:46, 1:01:38, 31:43
  - Johnson, Ken and Janet McLennan, 2006
    Johnson and McLennan each served for a time as Straub's Deputy State Treasurer, as well as served in his gubernatorial administration.
    - 3/16/2006
      Formats: 1 MiniDV tapes, 1 DVD access copy
      Length: 1:01:44
      An excerpt from their interview is found in the Excerpts subseries, and includes an accompanying transcript.
  - Kramer, Bud, 2005
    Loren (Bud) Kramer served as administrative assistant and later executive assistant to Straub during his governorship. Kramer also served as a Cannon Beach city councilor, an administrator of the Department of Environmental Quality, and as a member of the Law Enforcement Council, among other public service positions.
    - 4/29/2005
      Length: 1:02:28
    - 5/5/2005
      Length: 1:02:31, 53:00
      In this interview, conducted in his Portland home, Kramer discusses his years at Reed College and as a precinct organizer; relates stories about Oregon policitians such as Edith Green, Richard Neuberger, and Charles Porter; and compares political campaigns in Straub's day with those of the present.
    - 5/27/2005
      Length: 1:02:07, 39:23
  - Linde, Hans and Helen, 2004
    Hans Arthur Linde was a Legislative Assistant for Sen. Dick Neuberger from 1955-1958, a University of Oregon law professor from 1959-1976, and an Oregon Supreme Court Associate Justice (appointed by Straub) from 1977-1990, among other positions. He and his wife Helen were longtime friends of the Straubs.
    - 11/4/2004
      Length: 1:02:26, 44:26
  - McCall, Audrey, 2005-2006
    Audrey McCall was the wife of former Oregon Governor Tom McCall. Following her service as First Lady, she continued to be politically involved in support of enivironmental issues such as the Bottle Bill, salmon protection, and strong land use planning laws.
    - 9/27/2005
      Formats: 1 Digital8 tape, 1 DVD access copy (combined with the 2/16/2006 interview recording)
      Length: 55:50
    - 2/16/2006
      Formats: 1 MiniDV tape, 1 DVD access copy (combined with the 9/27/2005 interview)
      Length: 53:50
  - McKay, Floyd, 2003-2004
    Floyd McKay, a journalist (most notably for Portland's KGW-TV) and a friend of Straub's, also served as Gov. Neil Goldschmidt's press secretary and as a journalism professor at Western Washington University.
    - 11/28/2003
      Formats: 2 Digital8 tapes, 3 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:47, 46:38
    - 8/3/2004
      Length: 51:41
  - McLennan, Janet, 2003-2004
    Janet Watts McLennan served as Deputy State Treasurer under Straub, and later served in his gubernatorial administration as his Natural Resources Assistant. After Straub left office, she went to work for the Bonneville Power Administration (BPA). Highly involved in environmental issues, she was influential in the Beach Bill and spearheaded the Committee to Save the Beaches (later named Beaches Forever, Inc.).
    - 11/8/2003
      Formats: 2 Digital8 tapes, 3 DVD access copies. Video files and transcriptions are available online.
      Length: 1:01:45, 54:51
    - 1/25/2004
      Length: 1:01:48, 1:01:47
    - 3/20/2004
      Formats: 3 Digital8 tapes, 6 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:01:45, 1:01:48, 15:37
  - Meier, Roger, 2003-2004
    Roger Meier served as a member of the Oregon Investment Council alongside Straub, and was President and CEO of AMCO, Inc., a private investment company.
    - 12/3/2003
      Formats: 1 Digital8 tape, 1 DVD access copy (combined with the 1/19/2004 interview)
      Length: 59:30
    - 1/19/2004
      Formats: 1 Digital8 tape, 1 DVD access copy (combined with the 12/3/2003 interview)
      Length: 1:01:48
    - 3/24/2004
      Formats: 1 Digital8 tape, 1 Hi8 tape, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 58:30, 24:16
  - Miller, Fred, 2006
    Fred Miller was appointed as director of the Oregon Department of Energy by Straub. Prior to that he served as an economist for the State Transportation Department, and in 1981 he was appointed as director of the Oregon Department of Transportation.
    - 3/29/2006
      Length: 1:04:19, 45:50
  - Redden, Jim, 2005
    James Anthony (Jim) Redden, Jr., an Oregon attorney, politician, and judge, served in a variety of public offices, including as State Treasurer (succeeding Straub) and as State Attorney General.
    - 11/2/2005
      Formats: 1 MiniDV tape, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 55:48
  - Rippey, Jim, 2006
    James (Jim) Rippey, a leader in the mutual fund industry, co-founded and served as the president of Columbia Management Company and Columbia Trust Company.
    - 6/6/2006
      Length: 1:01:01
  - Roberts, Barbara, 2004-2006
    Barbara Roberts served as Oregon's first female governor, from 1991-1995. She first entered politics as an autism advocate, and went on to serve as a State Representative and as Secretary of State before becoming governor. In addition to being an advocate for gay rights, public transit, and tax reform, she was a strong supporter of environmental issues.
    - 10/22/2004
      Length: 1:01:49, 49:34
    - 10/25/2004
      Length: 1:02:30, 1:02:27
    - 12/17/2004
      Length: 58:02, 54:43
    - 2/10/2005
      Length: 1:02:30, 17:43
    - 3/15/2005
      Formats: 2 MiniDV tapes, 3 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:00, 1:02:22
    - 3/28/2005
      Length: 1:02:32, 1:02:18
    - 3/29/2005
      Length: 45:21
    - 5/6/2005
      Length: 1:01:53
    - 6/13/2005
      Length: 1:02:33, 1:01:44
    - 6/21/2005
      Length: 1:02:10, 51:46
    - 10/26/2005
      Formats: 1 Digital8 tape, 2 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:12
    - 11/8/2005
      Length: 1:00:37, 1:00:09
    - 2/28/2006
      Length: 1:02:22
    - 3/14/2006
      Length: 13:44, 1:02:36
    - 3/30/2006
      Length: 1:00:41, 49:42
    - 3/31/2006
      Length: 1:00:18, 52:49
  - Russell, Jean, 2003
    Jean Straub Russell, Bob's younger sister, remained close to Bob throughout their lives, and their families often vacationed together. Jean and her husband Ike lived in Tucson, Arizona, and had two sons, Luke and David.
    - 7/8/2003
      Length: 1:01:10, 29:00
  - Shepherd, Ruth, 2005
    Ruth Shepherd served as special assistant on elderly programs in the Oregon Department of Human Resources during Straub's gubernatorial administration. She also served on the Lane Transit Board and Eugene School Board, and was an ongoing advocate for senior citizens' issues.
    - 2/28/2005
      Length: 1:02:27, 47:27
  - Straub, Jeff, 2005
    Jefferson Tully (Jeff) Straub is Bob Straub's oldest son. He served in the Air Force and worked in mining, among other positions, and now lives with his wife Kelly in Ashland, Oregon. He ran for the State Senate in 1986.
    - 9/13/2005
      Formats: 3 MiniDV tapes, 4 DVD access copies
      Length: 1:02:28, 1:01:04, 21:26
  - Straub, Mike, 2005
    Michael (Mike) Straub is the second son of Bob and Pat Straub. He worked primarily in construction, both for his father and on his own. He and his wife Linna live in Springfield, Oregon.
    - 8/30/2005
      Length: 1:02:31, 56:20
    - 10/29/2005
      Length: 47:45
  - Straub, Pat, 2003
    Several years after first meeting Bob Straub at Mt. Moosilauke, Patricia (Pat) Stroud married him in 1943; the couple had six children. In addition to raising their children and supporting Bob's political efforts, Pat Straub was a watercolor artist, a gardener, and an advocate of environmental issues; she published a book on organic cooking and gardening, From the Good Earth.
    - 9/11/2003
      Formats: 1 Hi8 tape, 1 DVD access copy, 1 audiocassette access copy of the audio of the interview
      Length: 1:00:55
    - 10/2/2003
      Length: 1:02:32, 30:52
      Topics discussed in this interview include Bob's entry into politics as Lane County Commissioner, his family's help in campaigning, Straub's first campaign for State Senate, his motivations for running for State Treasurer, and camping trips with family and friends.
    - 10/21/2003
      Length: 1:01:04, 23:00